[Music]
Stanford
University let's begin with a little
mathematical preliminary a few
mathematical
preliminaries um which if I didn't do
them now in advance I would have to do
them during the course of showing you
some things about string theory and and
that would be a
nuisance on the other hand there's
nothing that I think you don't know well
or that most of you don't know well
first thing just a little bit of a
little bit of calculus formulas a couple
of calculus formulas that are useful to
have on the
Blackboard um if we have a
function and let's call the function X
that's the dependent variable X is a
function and what is it a function of
it's going to be a function of a
variable called
Sigma why am I using X why am I using
Sigma because it turns out that these
are the standard um notations that are
used in string theory for certain
function functions but they could be any
functions it could be y as a function of
X it could be X as a function of Sigma
it could be f as a function of g
whatever right and I'm going to allow
for the purpose of this discussion now
Sigma to be a variable which runs from
zero to
Pi in other words half a cycle around
the circle so Sigma is an angular
variable except it's not quite an
angular variable it's an angular
variable that only goes halfway around
the
circle
now I want to approximate a continuous
function by a discrete
function and
eventually make my description better
and better and better by filling in um
by filling in the axis with more and
more points that's what calculus does
for you so we replace X of Sigma by X
let's call it sub
I where I runs from
one to
n later on we're going to let N get very
very
big let's think of the
difference between X at I and X at I + 1
we can call that Delta X if we
like but it's Delta X between I and I +
1 or I and IUS one I think I made
it it's just equal to X of i - x of IUS
one I could have chosen it I + 1 - I
that's Delta X okay and it's well
approximated in the limit where we put
many many points in there assuming the
function is smooth in other words
assuming that the limiting function is a
smooth differentiable function it's well
approximated by derivative of x with
respect to Sigma time Delta
Sigma and how big is Delta
Sigma Delta
Sigma Delta Sigma is the sigma interval
between two neighboring values of Sigma
how big is that that's the whole
interval
pi divided by n chopped up into n little
segments all right so this is another
formula that we'll make use of and
finally a formula this is for
derivatives the formula for
integrals let's first imagine adding up
all the
X's sum of all the
XI we're adding them all
up what's the approximation for that
well if you multiply it by Delta
Sigma in other words just take Delta
Sigma which is pi/ n and multiply that
by the sum of the sigmas this becomes in
the limit the
integral in this case from 0 to
Pi of X of
Sigma we simply replace X of I by X of
Sigma and Delta Sigma becomes D
Sigma right basically it's a definition
of an integral but I want to have these
equations on the Blackboard because
we'll use them uh several times okay
that's the first mathematical
preliminary let's draw a line underneath
it I'm going to try to get all the
mathematical preliminaries on the
Blackboard over here and then use them
over there okay
next supposing we have a function now a
continuous
function actually it doesn't even really
have to be continuous but uh a function
take it to be continuous defined on the
interval from0 to
Pi any such function with a caveat that
describe in a minute any such function
can be Foria analyzed or another way of
saying is it can be written as a sum of
ss and
cosiness
uh SS and cosiness and I'll write out
and I'll give you examples in a moment
but before you do so I should say signs
or
cosiness uh before you do so before you
do it you have to establish certain
features about the
functions which put them in a class
which is either called derish or noron
anybody know what they are
dislay boundary conditions boundary
conditions boundary conditions the
behavior at the of the functions at the
end points the bound Aries of the
interval all right so for example this
function could stand for the
displacement of a violin string from the
horizontal for a hor for a horiz well
not for horizontal but for a violin
string you hold down the
ends the ends are firmly in place and
therefore the value of x at the ends is
zero just because the ends are being
held
fixed those are called dis or that is
called dislay boundary conditions I'll
write it once
de
L dis lay was a dis lay derish lay with
a T at the end dlay dlay of course was a
French
mathematician and studied waves moving
on things like strings and classified
one of the boundary conditions as dislay
and the meaning of that or dur slay
boundary conditions means X at the end
points that means X of 0 equals 0 and x
of
pi equals
z Now another class of
functions which
are sort of the opposite in a certain
sense uh well not the opposite but
they're just another class of functions
are described by something called nimon
boundary conditions nman of course was a
was a German mathematician NE e u m a n
n noyon boundary conditions and those
we're going to find those are the
appropriate conditions for discussing a
string the motion of a string and I'll
tell you where they come from as we go
along but at the moment I'm not doing
physics I'm doing just some mathematical
facts noon boundary conditions are the
statement that the derivative of the
function function is zero at the end
points so let's first draw a derish lay
function a dislay function might look
like this it's pinned down at the end
points and so X at the end points is
zero for nimon functions the derivative
of x with respect to
Sigma is equal to zero and those are
functions which look like this let's put
a vertical axis there too
vertical axis they don't necessarily go
through zero at the end points but their
derivatives go through zero that means
they have no derivative at the ends
here they're flat at the ends those are
Nyon functions or better yet that's the
Nyon boundary condition now why would
you impose one versus the other we'll
discuss that this is clear that you
would want to impose this if you had a
string which was held down when would
you use this basic the answer is when
you have a string whose ends are not
held
down uh but uh we'll come through
it both kinds of functions can be for
can be written as yeah I'm just going to
say with with a Viber phone or Viber
heart that's where you have a resident
bar supported quarter from
theend uh a um I'll tell where you would
use noon nle if you had an organ
pipe and if you close up the ends of the
Organ Pipe then the sound uh the sound
waves have to uh be zero displacement at
the ends if you open up the Organ Pipe
then uh the ends then it's Nyon boundary
conditions so uh
yeah yeah what if the string goes up
vertically at vertic uh
we're not talking about strings moving
in gravitational fields vertically and
horizontally are the same thing no I was
talking about Matic really if you come
up vertically as an approximation if it
comes up vertically and then is this oh
Oh you mean if it if it has a a vertical
jump in it yeah
um of course physicist as a rule don't
like such vertical jumps
discontinuities um discontin ities
usually mean Infinite Energy well I was
thinking of electric currents where you
could have a I was thinking of electric
current where you could have a a sharp
jump yeah yeah but even a really sharp
jump is even that is something that uh
yeah no you're allowed in inent you're
allowed to have sharp jumps in these
functions but they have to be peace wise
continuous peace wise continuous means
they can have jump here jump here but
they but we for our purposes in
particular for a
string um for a string to have a jump in
it would mean the string was broken yeah
and we don't want to break the
strings okay next thing aoria
decomposition or yes sir yes open pipe
satisfy that boundary condition what's
that the what the open pipe does it
satisfy that boundary condition well
it's more likely to satisfy this one
than this one wondering why it satisfies
any bound
uh I'll have to think about it and I'm
the uh we we think about it but I'm not
prepared right now if it satisfies
anything it's going to be this
one um but uh we we come back to it
yeah the pressure at the end has to be
the atmospheric pressure which
is you're probably right I I I had I
don't want to think about it now I don't
want to get my head off uh uh I'll tell
you I'll give you an example of an
idealized string system which does
satisfy it
you have a pole over here okay and
another pole over here put into the
ground you have a light almost massless
ring which goes around these poles and
they're connected by a
string again X corresponds to the height
of the string let's say above the
surface of the Earth this kind of system
if these if these Rings were very very
light would have lay boundary conditions
instead of holding the end of the string
down the end of the string is free
floating okay so it's when the end of a
string is free floating like this that
Nyon conditions are appropriate now
that's not obvious that's not obvious
we're going to I'm going to explain the
physics about why the ends of strings
freely floating string ends satisfy this
but for the moment we're just dealing
with mathematics okay all right now
again let's come back to the Foria
decomposition of such functions and
Foria decomposition plays a very very
essential
role in so many things but in particular
string
theory functions which satisfy dislay
boundary
conditions those can be let's call them
F
ofx no not f ofx x of Sigma
can be written as a sum from n = 1 to
Infinity okay
of coefficients x sub n those are a set
of
coefficients times
s of NX n Sigma y s because signs are
the functions which vanish at the end
points s of NX for any n is zero at xal
0 and xal
Pi the most General function that
satisfies dish L boundary conditions and
which is continuous and for our purposes
continuous differentiable all the good
things the most General function which
satisfies that can be written as a sum
of of
uh oscillating functions like this right
this is durish
L what are the functions whose
derivatives are zero at 0o and
Pi
cosine cosine
NX cosine
NX for any n is flat at the end points
and there are enough cosiness cosine X
cosine 2X cosine 3x what is cosine of 0x
incidentally what is s let's begin with
S of 0x why didn't I start at n equal 0
what is s of
0x it's just sign of zero right which is
zero so there's no point in putting in a
term which is
zero okay what about cosine of
0x it's one and if the function happens
to have have an average if its average
isn't zero over the interval it will
start out with a constant term which is
just flat in other words a flat function
is a good Nyon function and so in this
case X of Sigma for
Nyon X of
Sigma is the sum from n equal 0 to
Infinity because zero is now a uh an
interesting case X of
n time cosine of n
Sigma what about the derivative of x
let's take the disly case what is the
derivative of x of Sigma with respect to
Sigma well if you differentiate a sign
what do you get you get a cosine
so if a function is D it's derivative is
noon and if a function is nman it's
derivative is D that's a
fact
uh good now the last mathematical FL I'm
FL the last mathematical fact that I'm
going to put on the
Blackboard is a fact about integrals
integrals of ss and
cosiness most of you know it anybody who
knows anything about Foria analysis
knows it if not here's the fact
supposing you take let's work with the
cosiness supposing I integrate from zero
to
Pi
cosine of n Sigma times cosine of M
Sigma what do I
get first what do I get if n is not
equal to m
you get zero if n is not equal to
M you start with one cosine and N is not
equal to M it means
you're you're multiplying one cosine by
another cosine and as most of you know I
suspect that if you do that and
integrate it and average the product of
them you'll get zero okay so this is
zero if n is not equal to M what if it
is what if n is equal to
M then it's just well then of course
it's just integral cosine
squar of n
Sigma so how do you figure that out
let's say cosine integral of cosine
squar n
Sigma Co what does cosine squar vary
between it varies between zero and one
in fact the square of the cosine if the
cosine if some cosine function looks
like
this
oops if some cosine looks like that the
square of
it will of
course wherever it's one it'll stay one
but where it dips below the axis here
the square will be above the axis so the
square of it looks like
this
the square of it looks like that what is
the average of the
cosine zero what is the average of the
cosine squared a half all right so in
particular if you integrate cosine
squared you can just say the average of
cosine squar is a half but you're
integrating it between zero and
PI right so this function on the average
is just a
F but when you integrate between 0 and
Pi you get the width of the interval the
width of the integral and this is just
Pi / 2 it's Pi / 2 for any n and
M sorry no for any n equal to
M okay so we can write down now that
this is
equal the Delta n m that's the symbol
which is zero if n is not Al to M and 1
if n is equal to M * < /
2 now I made a mistake for one special
case anybody know what the special case
is n equals 0 so let's take n equal 0
integral 0 to Pi of cosine what's cosine
Sigma 1 all right cosine of 0 is 1 so
it's just one the sigma and that's equal
to
Pi so the one exceptional
case is when n and M are both equal to
zero okay this is
true this is true for n i I won't bother
writing it is it
exceptional I think so no no I was going
to say if only one of them is zero but
that's okay well yeah if one of them
zero and the other is not at zero yeah
okay no then then it's it's not
exceptional that way
except n = m = z and then we
get
Pi just Pi these are some mathematical
facts that we will
need all right the other thing that I
had planned to write out is a bunch of
mathematical facts but I think I'll hold
off on it we'll come back to it uh is
properties of harmonic oscillators yes
let me just write down one fact about
harmonic
oscillators uh if you have a harmonic
oscillator described by a coordinate
X then the harmonic oscillator a hooks
law
oscillator the um the coordinate of the
oscillator you could write as X whether
or not it's the same X as here we'll
come back to but for the moment let's
just call a coordinate of the oscillator
the displacement of the oscillator X
what is the kinetic
energy what's the kinetic energy of
[Music]
uh what's the kinetic energy of the
point 12 m x do^ squ right 12 M time the
time derivative of X2 but you can always
work in
units in which the mass is equal to one
you can always rescale things you can
rescale a coordinate so that MX do
squared is just you take you take the m
and you take the square root of it you
absorb it in here and you rescale X you
can always choose units so that the
kinetic energy is X do squar and over
two it's conventional to put a two there
that's the kinetic energy of a point
Mass a point Mass what about the
potential
energy of a hooks law so this is energy
let's call it
energy that's plus 12 times the spring
constant call it
Kappa
X2 what's the frequency of this
oscillator can anybody tell me what the
frequency
is
yeah square root of K Over M but m is
one I've chosen M to be one I'm working
in a formulation where m is equal to one
so what is the frequency the frequency
is the square root of K or in other
words K is the frequency squared let's
just put it there Omega
squared this is uh the formula for a
harmonic oscillator this is its energy
kinetic energy potential energy
if we wanted to work with
lunians we would write kinetic energy
squar minus potential energy
squared okay that's uh that's the basic
formula that we'll need for harmonic
oscillators the quantum oscillator we
will come back to the quantum oscillator
is of course quantized with energies in
units of Omega so if you see this you
say uhhuh the energy levels of this
harmonic oscillator are any integer
times
Omega time H
bar right all right so I think we're all
on the same page on
[Applause]
that next question I want to address now
this is a perhaps a philosophical
question but uh but I think we have to
answer
it what is a particle what do we mean
mean by a particle we're going to be
talking about
strings strings are not particles
strings are assemblages of large numbers
of particles with springs between
them uh so in what sense do we mean what
mean what do we mean when we say a
certain particle is a
string that raises the question what do
we mean in general by a
particle all right so what properties do
particles have they have
location but uh um a
no particle is known to be a point in
fact no particle that is known is a
point period no particle that we know of
is a point particle even the electron is
not a point particle it has a little
cloud of photons around it the photons
have virtual
pairs uh the electron if you could look
at it through a powerful microscope
would have some fuzz around it and that
fuzz would be virtual photons and
virtual pairs electrons positrons so an
electron is not a point certainly a
proton or a neutron is very far from a
point those are big gigantic objects
that uh that
are why do I say big big is a relative
term and for this
class protons are very very big
so a particle is not a thing which is a
point particle it can be composite it
can be made of
things
what would you take let's take a thing
which I think most of us would not call
a particle ordinary
ordinarily let's take a box filled with
particles a box uh just an ordinary box
tint can filled with a large a gas of a
large large number of particles
it has a
mass it has a position namely the center
of mass position when we speak about the
position we usually mean the center of
mass position so the uh ah here it is
here's the here's here's the thing we're
talking about is it a particle of course
not it's a cup of coffee um it has a
position it has a
mass why don't we call it a
particle apart from the fact that it's
big and since I already said big is a
relative
term uh so then why is this not a
particle what other ingredient do we add
when we speak of particles but when
physicists speak of particles now I
don't expect you to know the answer I
will tell you the answer the anybody got
an answer
indivis indivisibility nope proton is
certainly not
indivisible spin
well stability if you turn it over the
coffee is going to fall
out naturally stable wait for I'm not
going to try it this particle happens to
have a hole in
it as a matter of fact I'm going to make
the hole bigger and I'm going
to okay I
will I will tell you what added
ingredient uh is important an important
distinction between things which we
usually think of as particles and things
which we usually think of as highly
composite it has to do with their energy
spectrum and if you remember that energy
is equal to mass eal
mc^2 then it has to do with their Mass
Spectrum an electron has a more or less
well it has a unique Mass okay the
electron you cannot add to the mass of
the electron I could add to the mass of
this very easily just shake it shake it
and stop shaking it why have I added to
the mass of
it because I've put some energy into it
that's probably stirred it up and uh and
added to its energy and energy is mass
electrons there is nothing that you can
do to increase the mass of an
electron I shouldn't say nothing nothing
that we can do in the laboratory at
present can excite the electron into a
state of higher Mass it's discrete it's
it's all by itself it's energy Spectrum
if you were to plot vertically the
energy here would be the electron right
over there the photon would be down at
the bottom with zero Mass there would
not be a whole bunch of excited states
of the electron just above
it the proton does have excited States
but the excited states are pretty pretty
discreetly different than the proton
than the proton itself it takes a couple
of hundred me million electron volts to
spin up a proton or to cause it to
oscillate so a proton also has to some
extent this uh discreetness and the
excitations of it are well above it
right so it's it's got a kind of
isolation in energy or in Mass what
about cup of coffee a cup of coffee has
a mass of some fraction of a
kilogram but what if I stir it up a
little bit so it's over here it's up
here at one kilogram not less than a
kilogram what about the first excited
state of the coffee if I were to cool
the coffee down to zero temperature it
would have some
Mass how much energy can I add to it I
can add an incredibly tiny amount of
energy to it
why well one way is just to poke one
molecule and give it but even less
energy by making a a sound wave through
it a phoneon through it an incredibly
tiny amount of energy and so there's a
neighboring state right there which is
so
close that you really can't distinguish
it as a separate indivis individual
Quantum State and there are zillions of
them zillions of states very close by
practically forming a Continuum of
energy l
levels that is in practice how we
distinguish particles from uh from
mush mush can be excited by tiny tiny
little bits of energy particles it takes
a significant discrete amount of
energy uh an identifiable discrete
amount of energy to excite them that's
really the only
difference is a string a Quantum string
a particle or not and that depends on
the excitation spectrum of the energy
levels above the ground state if they're
well separated for some
reason then the answer is it will behave
like a particle if they're extremely
close together so close together that
the experiment whatever it happens to be
can't distinguish them then it won't
behave like a
particle uh
that's the characteristic difference
between mush as I said in
particles the energy that it takes to
perturb a proton is a couple of hundred
meev oh some uh 15 15% of its own Mass
to get the excited state of the proton
maybe more like 20
um oh about 50% of its mass 40% of its
mass to get up to the next energy level
so that's pretty
significant what about a string a
Quantum string well the strings that
we're going to talk about the particular
ones we're going to talk about the
separation between the first string and
its excited state is more like the plunk
mass and that's a huge Mass from an
experimental point of view so huge that
we have no hope of in a laboratory
exciting the
excitations so
[Applause]
um that's why we call strings particles
yeah so is this like an issue of scale
then because if you zoomed in you would
see those different energy levels being
far if you're looking close enough the
energy levels are the energy levels if
you zoomed in you might be able to see
that it was made out of a lot of pieces
but nevertheless you would discover that
even though it's made out of a lot of
pieces uh to excite them would call cost
a very large amount of energy on the
scale of particle physics energy levels
in other words if you were to try if an
electron is is truly a
string and its mass is what half an Mev
or something like that and the
excitation energy to rotate it or to
vibrate it or to do anything else to it
is the plunk Mass which is how many
times bigger than the electron I mean 10
23 10 24 times bigger so there's a big
gap in the Spectrum the existence of
gaps in the spectrum is what defines
what makes particles different than
uh
uh how about a violin
string very little very little energy by
comparison with its actual mass if the
violin string is made out of cat G what
do they make violin they still make cat
they still kill cats to make
violins yeah yeah
okay
um you know less than a gram I don't
know what but uh but it's you know it's
a significant mass and the energy that
it would take to excite one Quantum
worth of energy to that violin string
when translated into mass is
unmeasurably small so you've got a lot
of quantum States in a tiny little
interval a violin string is not
something we would call a
particle
okay so now we have to begin to
explore the mathematics we have the
mathematics on the Blackboard I suppose
we should say we're exploring the
physics but uh but the physics is is
fairly
mathematical so so a photon is not a
point particle a photon is a point
particle a it's not a question of point
it's a
particle there's no similar particle
with a mass very close to it
no no I I was agreeing that it's a
particle but the question is whether you
said there's no such none of the
particles are Point particles no um a
photon is not a point particle a photon
can dissociate into an electron and a
proton and a positron not a proton an
electron and a positron so if you were
to look at a proton carefully you would
find out it's also a fuzzy structure
with uh electron positron pairs in it
more virtual photons
um it's pretty darn small but uh not
infinitely
small and it's even measurably it has
measurable size to it you can actually
measure the size of the the fact that a
electron for example is not a point is
um Associated among other things with
its anomalous Magnetic
Moment a phon size depend on its
frequency no no not
uh not in the correct definition of it
no it's wavelength does but not its
physical
size
okay now we talked the last time about
um describing systems at very very large
momentum this is an important part of
the logic of uh of the approach the
string theory we're going to take it's
called the like cone frame or the
infinite momentum frame and I'll just
remind you for the moment we we we could
come back to it at some later time but
at the moment the main fact that we
established though that we talked about
last time is that if you take a system
which could be highly relativistic what
it means to me highly relativistic now I
mean that it has Parts pieces which move
relative to each other with close to the
speed of light okay a baton twirled
around so fast the ends of the Baton are
moving with close to the speed of light
that's a very relativistic system and
the question is can you in any sense at
all describe it using something like
non-relativistic
physics if the Baton is moving
slowly so that all parts of it are
moving with only a small fraction of the
speed of light then of course you use
non-relativistic physics to describe it
but it's an
approximation it really and as it spins
faster and faster as the parts of it get
up relative velocities relatively close
to the speed of light that approximation
breaks down it's not a good
approximation so it's in no sense exact
even if the Baton if the center of mass
of the Baton is at rest the issue of
using non-relativistic physics to
describe the relative motions of the
pieces of it is not a question of
whether the the center of mass of it is
at rest it's a question of the relative
motions so there's no good approximation
no good non-relativistic approximation
to a baton which is spinning fast enough
that its parts are in relativistic
motion relative to each other on the
other hand the trick that I showed you
last time is exact it's exact in the
following sense you could take the baton
twirling around an axis going uh in this
direction altogether and now boost it
all you have to do in order to bring it
into the non-relativistic form that I
talked about last time is just boosted
to a
momentum where the momentum of the whole
thing is much larger than the momentum
going around in the
plane or equivalently it's much more
relativistic along the axis that you
boosted it than it is in the other
directions then the formulas I showed
you last time become exact and what do
they say they say that with respect to
the two-dimensional
motion the two-dimensional Motion in the
plane perpendicular to the direction
that you boosted it up the description
is completely and exactly
non-relativistic
so that was the trick that we used or
that we're going to use to describe the
proper of
strings and it's that trick which makes
it which gives me the courage to explain
it to this class because I wouldn't try
to explain it in the fully relativistic
form
uh yeah last week you referred to the
infinite momentum that's what I'm
talking about yeah so if truly was
infinite then that would imply that is
traveling is a speed of light you just
slightly off slightly
off slightly do you want me to go
through that again just very
briefly I don't know so I understand the
concept just a question whether it's
truly infinite or really really big no
no you take limits you take limits you
define things which have limits all
right let me let me show you the sorts
of things you can Define which yeah
what's the axis that the Theon is
rotating you just pick an axis any axis
any axis no matter how the system is
moving pick any axis and boost it along
that axis what if it's being boosted
along the same axis that it's
rotating perpendicular to it well if
it's rotating this
way um the axis is that way no what if
it's being boosted in the same axis that
it's then it's moving this way it still
has a nonrelativistic description what
it would look like
nonrelativistically from the
non-relativistic point of view is a rod
which is doing this projected onto the
plane the projection onto the plane is
non relativistic
and uh the Curious Thing about strings
it's it's completely enough to know
their projection onto the plane to know
everything about them this is a bizarre
and interesting fact about
strings that uh they do not have any
independent coordinates if you boost
them along an axis they have no
independent degrees of freedom along the
axis all the degrees of freedom are
perpendicular to the
axis uh it's a rather remarkable fact
about them
amplify that though in that means they
can't arbitrarily move in that they can
no they can't arbitrarily move in that
direction the motion in that direction
is completely determined by the motion
in the other
directions yeah that's uh and trapped in
a in a like in a sandwich sort of well
they are trapped in a sandwich in that
direction but it's more than that it's
not just that they're trapped in a
sandwich that their motion well first of
all they Len contracted all right but in
you know if you find to
F uh examined within that lorence
contraction yes they would be moving but
their motion is completely and entirely
dictated by the motion in the other
directions that's a that's a curious
fact is that the source of the
holographic princip yeah well it was one
of the things it was one of the things
that uh that the speculation began yeah
it is yeah it is closely connected with
that um
and I don't think we're going to try to
get into that now for
sure instead we're just going to well
all right let me uh let me just remind
you about that light cone story let's
let's spend two minutes at
it you take any
system collection of particles moving
doing whatever they're doing it has a
center of mass in the frame of reference
at which the center of Mass is at rest
it has an energy that energy is called
its rest
energy and it's the thing which when
divided by c^ S you call the mass
multiply divided all right the energy at
rest means the energy when its momentum
is zero in a frame of reference in which
its momentum is zero that's called the
rest
Mass it doesn't have to refer to a
single
particle it can refer to any system
whatever in in the frame of reference in
which it is has zero momentum in other
words in the frame of reference which
it's at rest in that frame of reference
its energy is called rest energy or rest
Mass okay so it has a mass that mass is
in general composed not only of the
masses of the
constituents but the relativistic motion
the kinetic energy and even their
relativistic kinetic energy whatever it
is it all adds up to the mass now now
what if it's moving if it's moving it
has an energy which is not just m it's
the square
root of the momentum squared plus the
mass squared I've set c equal to 1 speed
of light equal to
one that's the formula for the energy of
it and let's write that in the form
Square TK of p z^ 2 that's the direction
we're going to boost along
plus I could write px2 + P y^2 but I'm
not I'm just going to write p² P well
let's just call it px^ 2 ah why not px2
plus P
y^2 plus M
squared when you boost the system along
an axis let's say the z-axis the other
components of momentum don't change so
as long as these components of momentum
are finite you can always make p pz much
bigger than anything else in the problem
bigger than PX and py and much bigger
than M and in that limit this
becomes equal
to
pz plus px^ 2 + p y^
2 divided by twice
pz plus m^2 / tce pz what I've done is
expand this quantity here thinking of pz
as the big thing and the rest of it as
being much smaller and this is what you
get right now first thing is well this
does not look like it has a good limit
as it
stands when pz gets large first of all
it gets large it gets
infinite right but what is this Infinity
this
[Music]
Infinity is
notice that this Infinity does not
depend on the X momentum the Y momentum
or even all the internal motions which
are making up the mass it's just a
constant which doesn't depend on the
internal structure of what's going on
inside the object it's just the momentum
you can subtract it off this is a rule
if you have a conser
quantity a quantity which is conserved
and which uh whatever it is you can
subtract it from the energy because in
the end of the day the only things
you're interested in are energy
differences generally speaking uh at
least before you worry about gravity the
only things we worry about about energy
is energy differences between
systems um so you can either subtract it
off or bring it to the left hand side
you can write e minus
pz and not worry about uh
about adding the pz there because it
simply never contributes to differences
of energy of different things for
example if this were an atom an atom
might Decay what an atom does when it
decays is related to the energy
difference between the states which
Decay this as long as the atom's
momentum along the z-axis doesn't change
during the Decay this term here doesn't
uh doesn't amount to anything now what
about the pz and the denominator why is
that
there keep in mind that energy is
related to
time that energy is hamiltonian and
hamiltonian in quantum mechanics has to
do with the rate at which the wave
function
changes and energy is hamiltonian and
hamiltonian is i d by
DT the time derivative of the wave
function why is the right hand side
going to zero if the right hand side is
going to zero the leftand side must be
going to zero in other words the wave
function must be changing very very
slowly for a particle moving with a
large
momentum the internal wave function the
wave function having to do with its
internal motions why is it that the
internal
motions look like they're going slow
time dilation time dilation so what you
want to imagine then is you want to
rescale the time the faster the system
goes down the z-axis the slower its
internal motions but we don't want to
throw away the internal motions we want
to keep track of them we want to
understand them so we rescale the time
in other words we go to a Time variable
which as we boost the
system we go to a Time variable which is
suitably redefined so that the internal
motion if it was a if it was an atom we
would want to rescale a time so that the
atom so that the rate of um of
revolution of the electrons around the
atom would not go to zero and that
simply means throwing away the pz in the
denominator the pz is the time dilation
Factor if we don't care about it and we
want to speed up everything by going to
a new time variable all we have to do is
throw away the pz in the
denominator I suppose that's equivalent
to multiplying by pz and now you see we
have an expression on the right hand
side which does not which sorry which
does have a limit as pz goes to
Infinity it's the hamiltonian or the
energy
function which keeps track not only of
the internal motions but the Motions
along the X and Y
Direction the Motions along the X and Y
direction as well as the internal
motions are kept track of by a
hamiltonian over here and it has a nice
limit as pz goes to Infinity number one
number two it looks very
non-relativistic the sums of the squares
of the momentum compon of momentum or
the square the momentum divid by two
that's the Rel yeah what happened to The
Peculiar PG what peculiar pz it's
dropped out the individual comp well no
no we have to worry about the relative
pzs to some
extent
um if the system is composed of a bunch
of parts the other coord the other
degrees of freedom that we have to keep
track of is the ratio of momentum along
Ong the z-axis of the different parts
but in string theory you don't have to
worry about it this is quite a Marvel of
string theory you don't ever have to
worry about it it's all constrained in
the but that it is missing there it is
missing there yeah well it's it's not
missing here because here I'm thinking
about a total system but if the system
is made up out of parts then each part
would have would give a contribution
that looks like this well yeah last week
you were summing so I part here I've
written the expression for the entire
composite system okay but the composite
system of Madea Parts this would be the
center of mass motion this would
correspond to the center of mass motion
the center of mass Motion in the
two-dimensional plane if the system is
made of a bunch of parts so that the PS
here are sums of momentums of other
particles then yes in principle you
should have to worry about the relative
uh components along the
z-axis um and if you really had to worry
about them it would be very complicated
string theory for Magical reasons that
are only partially understood but uh no
they're understood um but still a little
bit magical the relative motion of the
parts along the z-axis is completely
constrained and completely determined by
the other motions so you don't even have
to think about it just throw it away
don't worry about
it it's it's not intuitively obvious but
uh but it is
true okay so the main message here is
that the physics of a very fast moving
system as it moves in the uh in the
perpendicular
plane has the form has the exact this is
not an approximation exactly has the
form of two-dimensional non-relativistic
physics but what you have to keep track
of is that the portion of the energy
which is independent of the state of
motion the thing you would
nonrelativistically think of as
the um the bound The Binding energy of a
system just the energy at rest is not
proportional to the mass in this
formulation but it's proportional to the
square of the
mass okay so that's the that was that's
a review that's a 1H hour
review I will try not to make one hour
reviews for everything we do that will
uh but I thought uh this time it was
worth the effort okay in fact I don't
even think we've quite finished what we
said the last
time let's uh let's go
on let's go on to Strings
now the right model for what we're
talking about now is strings moving in
two Dimensions all right in a plane
perpendicular to the direction of the
large momentum so let the let the
dimension let the large momentum be
along the perpendicular to the
Blackboard then we want to make a model
of a relativistic
string which is wiggling around moving
stretching doing all the things that uh
that um strings
do but moving only in two Dimensions all
right to do that again I think I'm still
reviewing but I think it's worth it we
think of the string as a collection of
mass
points or we can begin by thinking of
the string is a collection of mass
points we're just going back
to this approximation
here capital N Mass
points capital N Mass
points n minus one Springs between them
think of a string as a collection of
mass points with little Springs between
them and minus one Springs
okay and an energy let's write down its
energy this is now non-relativistic
physics each particle has a kinetic
energy it's a sum of all of the
particles the kinetic energy is X do^
2ar over twice its
mass no times twice its mass no times
its mass over two I'll get that right
eventually
Mass over
two this is the I spring and when I
write X here I mean you have to add
every place I write X add in also y x
goes to
Y there are two directions that
everything can move in and I'll call
them X and Y I here does not stand for
for X and Y it stands for which particle
along here we're talking about
same thing plus myy do^ 2/ 2 that's the
kinetic energy and what about the
potential energy the potential energy is
something like
Kappa times XI or we could call it Delta
X did I call it Delta X before yeah
Delta X let's just call it Delta
X Delta x i^ 2ar /
2 where Kappa is the spring constant
between the Springs between neighboring
uh between neighboring Mass points
that's the energy what about the
lran that's the difference this is
kinetic energy potential energy lran is
kinetic energy minus potential energy so
we might want to write that down at some
point and exactly the same kind of
expression except where X everywhere is
replaced by y That's a string of
Point masses now we want to take the
limit in which n goes large so first of
all we need a parameter to label this uh
to label the positions or to label the
uh the mass points that parameter will
take to be called Sigma and it goes from
Zer to Pi that's arbitrary I could let
it go from zero to to one I could let it
go from 0 to two I can let it go from 0
to 2 pi it's just a labeling device we
label going from 0 to 0 to
Pi the reason for labeling from 0 to Pi
instead of from 0 to 2 pi is because
we're going to save going from 0er to 2
pi for closed strings rubber bands think
of this string as a rubber band that's
been cut open and has two ends
right a rubber band with which is closed
together will allow to go from 0 to 2 pi
so it's just an arbitrary reminder that
this is not a closed cyclic string we'll
do closed cyclic strings
too okay now what about the masses as we
let and we want the mass of the whole
string to remain fixed if each Mass
Point weighed a
gram and I let the number of mass points
go to Infinity what would happen to the
string we get incredibly massive that's
not what we want to do we want to keep
the mass of the whole string fixed but
subdivided into smaller and smaller
pieces so that means that the
mass should go as 1/
n in
fact I think we can just let it be 1
over
n we could let it be something else over
n we could let it be 2 over n this is
actually a choice of units this is an
arbitrary choice of
units uh in fact all the all the choices
I'm going to make now can be absorbed
into units so we let the mass go to as
one/ n and what will the total mass of
the string be now oh I'm sorry just a
moment let me go let me go back a sec
this Mass here is not the true mass of
the mass point it's the non-relativistic
analog Mass I shouldn't call it m
because then you'll identify it with
relativistic MC s Mass let's just call
it
mu mu stands for just a
parameter and it's the analog mass of
the uh all right so we'll let mu be 1/ n
what would the total analog mass of the
system be one
one
okay so this is a
string with n analog Mass
one if you go all right let's let's just
leave it at that for the moment with
analog Mass one what about the spring
constant what happens if you have a
bunch of very very stiff Str Springs
imagine you have a bunch of very stiff
Springs and because of that you can't
stretch it very much now we combine in
series a large number of these
Springs
what's the spring constant of the whole
thing is it easier to stretch or harder
to stretch it's much easier to
stretch the spring constant of the
composite spring of the compos the
composite spring is like 1/ n one over
divided by the number of uh the meaning
of that is if we want to keep the
composite spring
fixed if we want to keep the composite
spring fixed then we have to let the
spring constants of the individual
little Springs here get large or
small large large if we have a rubber
band and we stretch it it might have a
hooks constant of some normal number
easy to stretch but if you try to take
two of the neighboring molecules and
stretch them I guarantee you you would
have to put in a lot more Force to
stretch it uh between two neighboring
molecules so so the spring
constant K I think I will take to be
let's see n this is arbitrary this is
convention k = n over pi^ 2ar the pi
squared is put there only for the
purpose of minimizing the number of pies
and formulas at the end don't if you
don't want to worry about the pies just
ignore them they uh they play no
essential role in anything I put them in
in order to get rid of pies at some
later stage so don't worry about
them I I set nothing equal to one except
one sometimes I set some things like
three equal to
two but one not
one right I checked the the
normalization I want is uh the spring
constant as well but you can ignore that
all right let's rewrite these things as
integrals using uh exactly the uh the
formulas we have up there okay oh we
need one more formula Delta
Sigma is equal to Pi /
N I think I actually have that up there
do I yeah Delta Sigma is Pi / n taking
the pi interval and breaking it up into
end little pieces okay let's take the
kinetic energy first the kinetic energy
is going to be 1/
n times the sum of x i do^ 2 I'm only
going to do this for kinetic energy and
then I'll tell you what the answer is
for the potential energy all right now 1
/ n let's see 1 / n is Delta Sigma over
pi I've just divided this equation by pi
so let's see so this is equal to
sum Delta
Sigma 1 over
Pi time x i do^ 2 in fact I want XI do^
2 over
2 so that gives me a 1 over 2 pi out
here but now we use the connection
between integrals and sums a sum * Delta
Sigma is the same as an inte integral so
this just becomes integral 1 2 pi the
integral of derivative of x with respect
to Sigma squar uh with respect to time
squared derivative of x with respect
let's call it
too squared to is time to is this analog
or this time that appears in this uh in
these L cone or infinite momentum frame
physics
x dot means the xdt or the XD
to uh sum over a sigma times a function
is related is simply the integral and
where does the integral go from the
integral goes from 0 to
Pi that's the kinetic
energy what about the potential
energy I'm going to tell you now what
it's equal to
you can work it out yourself use exactly
the same things the new thing that we
need we have Delta X here and Delta X is
related to the derivative of x with
respect to Sigma right so the other term
that we get here
is plus derivative of x with respect to
Sigma
squar all times the
sigma have you seen the energy function
like that anywhere as
before if instead of
calling x x I called it a
fi and instead of calling Sigma Sigma oh
God I would call it
X in other words if I thought of Sigma
as a line in space and X as a field this
would be the energy energy of a simple
Mass a simple um wave field a simple
wave
field
uh and it would satisfy a wave
equation this physics here is exactly
the same physics as all wav like physics
waves run up and down this Sigma
interval now the only thing that you
have to keep track of is what happens
let's suppose we have a
wave go from
zero and supposing we have a
wave the wave either moves to the left
or the
right what happens to the wave when it
gets to the
end it doesn't keep going it bounces off
the boundary conditions either durish
lay or noon boundary conditions will
cause the wave the bounce off do you
know what happens to the wave when you
have Nora dish lay boundary
conditions yeah it gets flipped over it
gets flipped upside down in order to
keep uh the field here what happens with
Nyon boundary conditions then it just
flip then it just reflects uh with the
same
uh uh just it just reflects left to
right but it doesn't reflect up to
down all right so that's that's the
basic wave equation we could write down
the wave equation that corresponds to
this how would you write down the wave
equation well you'd write the lonian
lran is kinetic energy minus potential
energy and then you would work out lr's
equations Lan's equations would just be
a simple wave equation I'm not even
going to write it because we're not even
going to need it but it would just
describe waves moving up and down and
reflecting off the
ends
um what was to H what was TOA to was
time okay I'll tell you exactly what TOA
is remember that we had to rescale the
time because of the slowing down of
clocks okay um to is really proper time
it's
time the time of a clock that's moving
with our infinite imagine there's a
clock that we boost together with the
with the system that clock slows down so
we're not measuring real time in the
rest frame but we're measuring and
that's the system of interest is moving
next to the clock and so we can compare
the internal motions with the clock of
the system that's what this tow is okay
that's what this Tower is so it's time
except slowed down so that we can keep
track of the uh the time dilated
internal motions okay good but uh that's
what tow is
okay it's proper
time uh but you can just think of it as
time from the point of view of this
non-relativistic
um uh picture all right so that's the
energy of the
string and it has some
energy if the string is at rest in the
trans in this plane in other words if it
doesn't have any knit Motion in the
plane then its total energy will be the
square of the mass of the string
okay so we'll eventually use this
formula here to identify uh this energy
with the square of the mass of something
we'll come back to that a question on
question on mu again uh mu is is that
the the head that the mass of each
little Point yeah sorry of each point
mass and it's not M because m is the
rest mass and this is yeah yeah yeah
it's it's it's a it's a complete analog
object that uh that we don't even need
to specify we can just uh we can just we
can just write down this formula here we
just write down this formula yeah does
that quantity have a name e minus pz *
pz it's called the light cone
energy yeah the reason I don't want to
call it like cone is because it has
nothing to do with
cones um it's a
misnomer well no there a picture where
you rotate the
axes um you get the same same results
that you've gotten but some people find
it no no no no no the point is cones
cones cones these are not like cones
cones look like this these are the 45°
angles instead of the right those aren't
cones those are wedges cones around like
that Y and Z so the surface of
revolution of the I mean it's not no
it's not a surface of Revolution it's a
light front the right word would be
light front
yeah the wrong wrong terminology boosted
direction is not a cone right
right right it's two light planes
intersecting well don't worry about it I
I I purposefully didn't want to get into
that right there's no point in giving
you wrong terminology and then
explaining why it's a wrong terminology
my my my picture of a of a 4D 3D cone is
an expanding sphere this is not what
this is but this is not that not that
right right got nothing to do with
cones uh as I said it was a
misnomer light front would have been a
better word but didn't direct use the
term I don't think so I'm not sure I
don't know I don't think so no he just
did the
transformation right he did have light
cone coordinates but his like cone
coordinates were like cone coordinates
he also talked about something which I
would called light front coordinates he
uh and that was this so let's not let's
not belabor
it okay one last point before
we well I think all right I think all of
this we uh we went over last time and I
go over it more completely now now I
think I start with something that we
didn't go over last time I don't think I
did anyway did we talk about the
boundary conditions at the end of the
string and why they're noon and not
derish lay good let's do that now this
is
uh yeah okay let's leave this up on the
Blackboard here but now we want to come
to boundary conditions we want to come
to exactly this issue oh incidentally
let me let me reiterate again there's
another term and the other term is of
the same form except with Y replacing
X okay the motion of the string involves
knowing both both X and Y are as a
function of Sigma a point on the string
is labeled or is an X and A
Y okay so we have both of them and we
mustn't forget about them about the two
coordinates incidentally real String
Theory often makes use of many more
coordinates okay the many more
coordinates would just go into X Y give
me some more letters don't use Z because
we already used
WV and so
forth
gamma
Olive all right let's talk about
boundary conditions on the ends of
strings the boundary conditions are
actually determined by nothing more
complicated than Newton's law now you
say why are we allowed to use Newton's
Law we're talking about relativity well
it's because of this two-dimensional
analogy in the two-dimensional motion of
the string Newton's laws are correct now
Newton's laws appli to what Newton's
Laws applied to the mass
points Newton's Laws applied to the mass
points tell us how the mass points
accelerate given the force on them
what's the force on a mass point now a
typical Mass point is being pulled from
the left and it's being pulled from the
right so the
forces they they won't necessarily
balance but it will be getting a force
from the left and a force from the right
there are two special points which are
only getting forces from one side and
not the other those are the mass points
at the end of the string okay so let's
concentrate on the mass points at the
end of the
string
and then here's
the last point on the string the
ultimate point on the string that's n
and here's the penultimate Point N
minus1 and they're connected by a spring
now what is the
force the X component of force on the
endpoint of the string Hook's law H's
law tells you that the force on the end
of the string is the displacement or the
distance between the nth point and the N
minus first point in other words the
force on the string the force on the nth
Point here is proportional to Delta
X the
last let's just call it Delta X but it
means the separation between the nth
point and the N minus first point okay
that's the that's the force on oh sorry
what about the spring constant the
spring constant k
and if you remember K is very large it
grows like N I won't bother putting in
the pies so the force on the end of the
on the last molecule on the on the Chain
there is Delta X at Scales like Delta x
* n now what is Delta X Delta X is
approximately and in the limit of a
large number of points it becomes
exactly the derivative of x with respect
to
Sigma time Delta
Sigma and what is Delta
Sigma Delta
Sigma goes like 1/
n so the n's are going to cancel I don't
care about the numerical constant Factor
the force on the end of the
string is going to be
proportional let's just put
proportional to the derivative of x with
respect to Sigma what is the derivative
of x with respect to Sigma it's am the
amount that the string is stretched near
the end it's the stretching Factor near
the
end if the XD Sigma was Zero it would
mean the nth point and the N minus first
point are right on top of each other if
they're separated then there's a DX by D
Sigma now what does that have to equal
by by Newton's
equations by Newton's equations it has
to equal the analog
Mass
times the
acceleration M times let's call it xou
dot the
acceleration but what is the analog me
this isn't M this is
Mu but what is Mu mu because we've
chopped up the spring in the string into
lots of little pieces the end point is
very very light it has a mass which is
only one/
n
well now we have something a little bit
bizarre If I multiply this by
in let's multiply it by n let's get rid
of the intermediate thing here multiply
it by n we find that the acceleration
will go off to Infinity as n gets larger
and
larger okay the acceleration shouldn't
go to Infinity that doesn't make sense
that the acceleration of the endpoint of
the string is is wildly wildly violent
the answer is that the right boundary
condition at the end of the string is
noon boundary conditions so in order to
prevent infinite
accelerations which are quite unphysical
in order to prevent the string from
having an infinite acceleration at the
end point you impose noon boundary
conditions DX by D Sigma is zero at the
end
points
this was in fact the original argument
about all of this uh just uh uh it was
at this level that it was uh first uh
understood okay so now we have a fairly
complete system a system with a lran and
well-defined boundary conditions and the
question which we will take up after
about five minutes is how do you do the
quantum mechan mechanics of it that's
what we're after we're after the quantum
mechanical energy
levels we want to compute the quantum
mechanical energy levels and having
computed the quantum mechanical energy
levels we will know something about the
masses of these
objects that's the goal so we Mount we
can throw away everything else off the
Blackboard and say here is a system it's
a classical system at the moment how do
we make quantum mechanics out of it and
how do we uh how do we find its energy
levels now what do you do
to study this string and in particular
to study it quantum
mechanically well the first thing you
do is you write X as a sum over cosiness
remember what x is X is a function of
Sigma so is
y x is a function of Sigma Y is a
function of Sigma Sigma goes from zero
mpy what can we do to uh to make
a uh concrete um investigation of this
we can Foria analyze
X De no sorry noon boundary conditions
mean cosiness and so we write X of Sigma
in this form also y of
Sigma
and
then we take these two expressions let's
concentrate on X and we plug them into
the
lran or the energy it doesn't matter we
plug them into the energy or the lran
into the kinetic energy and the
potential energy and we redescribe the
system in terms of the kinetic and
potential energy of a set of new degrees
of freedom the new degrees of Freedom
are just these X ends and Y
ends so that's straightforward let's
let's begin with the kinetic energy
Let's see we I don't think we need
what's up
above so let's pull it down and start
with the kinetic energy I'll work it out
for you and then I'll probably well
maybe we'll do the potential energy too
once we have that we'll have something
that we can work with uh more easily
than this form here
okay so we
take xn we write it this way what's xn
dot dot meaning time
derivative sorry not what's xn do what's
x dot x dot of
Sigma X do of Sigma we just get by
differentiating this now the cosine of n
Sigma doesn't depend on on time at all
it's just the cosine of n Sigma it has
no time dependence does this have time
dependence
yeah something has to have time
dependence the string is going to wiggle
what has time dependence is the fora
coefficients the sigma dependence is
coded in these cosiness the time
dependence if x is also a function of
time in other words it's a wiggling
string it's a wiggling Str string the
position of every point on it is time
dependent the string Wiggles where do we
put the time dependence in these
formulas well we put them in
here so think of the X NS as being
objects which have a Time dependence
okay how about xn sorry X of Sigma dot
what is
that that's going to be someone in we're
just going to time differentiate we're
going to differentiate this with respect
to time term by term
so this is Nal
0 to
Infinity of I'll write it as xn
dot the time derivative of xn time
cosine n
Sigma now let's write the kinetic energy
to write the kinetic energy we first
have to write the square of this this is
the X this is the same as the
XD at Point Sigma all right we have to
square
it to square it will give us a double
sum so DX by D to^
squar will be a double sum a sum from
Nal
0 and m equal 0 to Infinity sorry m
equal 0 to
Infinity
x.n cosine n sign
I've just Rewritten this but then what
do I multiply it by I multiply it should
I do this in two
steps no okay
XM cosine M
Sigma all right so it's xn let's group
sorry XM dot let's group them together
xn
XM dot cosine n Sigma cosine M Sigma but
now we're also instructed to integrate
it to integrate it over Sigma integral D
Sigma the only Sigma dependence is in
these cosiness so we can bring the
integral over to here the sigma and the
last step is to divide by 1 over 2
pi the one over 2 pi is a convention
it's a convenient
convention
okay how about this
integral the inte has two kinds of terms
it has terms with n and M not equal to
zero and other terms and another term
with n and m equal to zero we have to be
a little bit careful about them uh first
of all after we've integrated over Sigma
there will be no terms with n not equal
to
M okay so in other words we're going to
get a single sum not a double sum
what'll be in the single sum it'll be 1
over 2
pi now the first term is going to come
from Nal 0 and m equal 0 and that is
just
x0 do^ 2ar ided
2 no no
two no no two at all not even any PI
yeah yeah yeah two and no
Pi where did that come from it came from
the pi canceling the pi downstairs
that's it right what is this what is
this x zero incidentally do you have any
idea what x0 stands
for it's the average position right but
that makes it the center of mass
position the center of mass position of
the string the string in addition to
everything else in addition to all of
its Wiggles it has a center of mass
motion it has a center of mass which is
its average position this is just the
kinetic energy of the center of
mass everything else is associated with
the internal vibrations and the internal
motions this is the piece that has to do
with the
overall motion of the
string so x0 and Y Z are nothing but the
center of mass okay let's let's suppress
Y and just work with X for a minute
now what about the other terms the other
terms are a sum from Nal 1 to Infinity
let's see what they have let's put them
in plus 1 over 2
pi xn do sared there are no terms with n
not equal to M and then what's the
integral of
cosine squar of n
Sigma Pi / 2 right Pi / 2 so the pies
will cancel and we'll get an extra
factor of two downstairs which will make
it overall a one
quar okay so this is Center of
mass
some and this here has to do with the
internal relative motions of the uh of
these little constituent elements of the
string now what about the other term
minus DX by D Sigma let's work that one
out I think I can erase this let's uh
let's get rid of this for a
minute let's work it out how about d x
by D
Sigma that's not x dot it's just d x byd
Sigma we start with this formula here
that's X and now we want to
differentiate it with respect to Sigma
what happens when you differentiate a
cosine of n Sigma with respect to
Sigma you get a
minus cosine becomes s but there's also
a factor of
in all right so there's an N here cosine
becomes
s so that's the derivative of x with
respect to Sigma notice if x involves
cosiness derivative of x with respect to
Sigma involves signs if one is D the
other is nman and vice versa okay so now
let's write down the square of DX by D
Sigma we'll be adding
then
plus a sum of N and M again because
we're going to square this when we
Square it the minus sign goes away and
we'll have n * m * xn
XM sin n Sigma
sin n Sigma sin M
Sigma and this gets
integrated what am I missing anything
yeah 1 over 2
pi okay what's the integral of the
integral of sin n Sigma time sin M Sigma
D Sigma from 0 to
Pi
same as for
cosine zero
unless zero unless n equal
m and if n equal
m pi over two I heard it I somebody say
it pi over two okay so again this all
adds up we're constrained to set n
equals to M by the integral the integral
will be zero unless n equal m okay okay
so it's just n^
2 xn
2 then pi over 2 right pi over 2 that
cancels the pi and puts a four
downstairs so it looks like this same
factor of a
quarter but instead of xn do^ 2 it has
n^ 2 * xn^
2 if we're doing the lran it's minus for
the lran it's minus for the energy it's
plus okay so we have three terms Al
together the first term involves X
notot the second term involves time
derivatives it's kinetic energy this is
of course is also kinetic energy kinetic
energy of the whole string and then
there's something which involves
X2 let's go back to
here this is the energy of a harmonic
oscillator energy of a harmonic
oscillator has an X do squared and an X
squar evidently for each
n the Lan is the lran of a harmonic
oscillator okay Gran of a harmonic
oscillator for each
n what are the frequencies of these
oscillators this system is a is a
collection an infinite collection of
infinite number of harmonic oscillators
it's as though you had an a discrete
countable Infinity of
Springs what are these of course these
are just the harmonics of the uh of the
string they're the harmonics of the
string and we what we've done is to
rewrite the lran in terms of the
coefficients of the individual harmonics
and what do you find first of all
they're not coupled to each other the
enth harmonic is not coupled to the m
harmonic it's a collection of un
non-interacting spring non-interacting
harmonic oscillators what's the
frequency of each one of these oscill
what's the frequency of the nth
oscillator yeah n
right you can read that off
from here it wouldn't change if you put
a four here the frequency would still in
both places as long as you put it in
both places Omega is the frequency and
Omega squar is the coefficient of x squ
here's the coefficient of x s and so we
can write there's a collection of
oscillators each one with a frequency
Omega n equal to
n
okay what about Omega
0er what happened to it you realize of
course that this is the restoring force
of the oscillators this is the restoring
this is the hooks law stretching energy
of the oscillators the restoring Force
there's no restoring Force for the
center of mass of course there's no
restoring Force for the center of mass
the center of mass is free to fly
away there's nothing holding on to the
center of mass so there's no restoring
Force
here that's just X do squared and the
internal energy this is the vibrational
internal energy of the
string it's this which has to be
identified where is it we lost it with
the mass squared the true Mass squared
of the relativistic string the internal
energy this is the internal energy and
it's to be identified with the square of
the
mass okay we might as well get rid of
this this is we could we it's it's
trivial it's just the overall Center of
mass motion this is the interesting part
here and as I said it's a collection of
harmonic oscillators now I've written
only half of it the other half are the
Y's so another identical it's a doubly
infinite collection of harmonic
oscillators each one with frequency n so
the first one has frequency one it's a
nice slow frequency the next one has
twice the frequency the next one has
three times the frequency and of course
these are simply the different um
different harmonics of the
string and what do we do with them we
quantize them we quantize them we
subject them to the process of
quantization which is very easy for a
harmonic oscillator in fact we don't
even really have to go through the whole
exercise we've done it before we just
have to remember that the energy of
harmonic oscillators are quantized in
certain
forms uh let's see if we can see what
the what the energy levels are going to
be there's going to be a lot of energy
levels an infinite number of course but
we can make uh some energies in a uh we
we can start organizing
them I think for tonight I won't write
down creation and Annihilation
operators and let's for the moment
suppress why we'll come back to Y let's
just concentrate on X
um H maybe we'll include now let's do Y2
let's do y two so for each n there are
two kinds of oscillators an oscillator
along the xaxis and oscillator along the
Y AIS okay all right so let's see what
the and they have the same frequencies
the X oscillate the X the X NS don't
have the frequency same frequencies the
x's and the Y's have the same frequency
so there's another replica of exactly
the same
thing and of course they correspond to
whether the harmonic is vibrating along
the x- Axis or the y-
axis by combining them together you can
make oscillations along different
axes right so let's see what kind of
energy levels a system will have um
there'll be a ground state where none of
the oscillators are excited they're all
in their ground state let's call that o
ground state this does not correspond to
the vacuum doesn't correspond to an
empty space it corresponds to a single
string with no energy
excitation right so it's a string it's a
it's a a form of particle it's got an
energy it's got a momentum and it has a
gap in its
Spectrum it has a gap to the next energy
level because harmonic oscillators have
gaps to the next energy the quantum
harmonic oscillator it takes some energy
some finite energy to excited so it's a
particle all right what's the first
excited state the first excited state
you can
create by creating one unit of X
energy how much does that correspond to
it corresponds to the frequency remember
the energy levels I should write down a
formula the energy of a harmonic
oscillator is equal to n h bar
Omega Omega this is different n
different n number of Quant what shall I
call it q q number of
Quant number of Quant it's an integer
it's an integer different integer than
these integers these integers label
different
oscillators but each oscillator itself
can be
excited all right so we we take the
energy
of a oscillator is Q the integer Q times
the frequency we're going to set plunk
constant equal to one let's forget plunk
constant set it to
one and
Omega is just
n so for the nth
oscillator it's just Q *
n for the nth oscillator the energy of
the nth oscillator all right so what's
the first
excitation you can excite yeah you can
excite either the x or y oscillator the
lowest oscillator the N equals 1
oscillator you can excite it one time
you can give it one Quantum of
energy okay how much energy does it have
then Q is one n is one it has one unit
of energy in some units we haven't
specified units yet so whatever the
ground St state is there's two states
above it two states Above It Whatever
the energy of the ground state let's not
specify the ground state energy it is
whatever it is above it this is the
ground state above it are two states why
do I say two
states either X you can you can asside
it along the x- Axis or the y axis it
just corresponds to the string vibrating
or to the um to the first oscillator
vibrating along the x-axis or the Y AIS
and of course linear superpositions of
them can vibrate along any
axis so that's the first thing one unit
up two states a multiplicity of two I
I'll put here the multiplicity the
multiplicity of this one is unique the
multiplicity of this one is two possible
orthog two possible
States what's what comes
next well you can do a number of
things you can
excite the lowest
oscillator twice you can excite the
lowest X oscillator twice you can excite
the lowest y oscillat
twice you can excite the lowest X
oscillator and the lowest y oscillator
each once but what else can you
do you can excite the second
ulator we'll do we'll work this out more
carefully next time when we introduce
creation and Annihilation operators but
you can excite either the x or the Y
lowest oscillator once that will give
you two units of energy up
here or you can excite the X lowest
oscillator once and the Y lowest
oscillator once that will also give you
two units of energy but you can also
excite the
second
oscillation once either X or Y that will
give you two more so Al together there
are five states
here five states X excited twice y
excited twice X once y once or the
second oscillator of either the x or the
y t type twice only
four I got
five one and one is okay so let's count
Let's see we can take the let's in terms
of creation Annihilation operators a for
x b for
y i we can take the lowest
oscillator
A+ sorry A1 one uh twice
squared uh
B1 plus squared on o this is exciting
the X oscillated twice the Y oscillated
twice a + 1 b + 1 o that's three
and
next
a2+ or B2
plus I no five states right five
states all
right uh exercise count the next uh the
next two levels how many states are
there all
together and
uh it's a exercise for the next time but
the point is the most important point is
that there are
gaps between
significant significant gaps between the
states so they're discrete they're
particle
like
um we'll work out in a little more
detail the Spectrum and then having done
all of that we'll try to identify some
of these particles some of them are bad
guys that we want to get rid of others
are good guys that are that we recognize
and we say those are particles that we
like having done that we want to do
closed
strings let me just tell you right now
in the next five minutes or next two
minutes what the relationship these are
called open strings they're open strings
because they have
ends all right they have end
points now the basic process of
interaction of string
theory
is stringin coming together and joining
to make longer strings strings can come
together if you like in the context of
hron physics Meson
physics the strings have quirks at the
ends quirks and Quirk anti- quarks now
that's not true for fun for the string
theories that we're going to be
interested in but for ordinary hron
quarks and
antiquarks and what can happen is a
quark and an antiquark can come together
annihilate and create a longer string so
the basic interaction process which we
haven't taken up yet we haven't
discussed it yet is the joining and
splitting if joining can happen
splitting can
happen joining and splitting of strings
now here's a string all by itself
and as it happens this
string executes a fluctuation which
happens to bring the other end around
close to the original
end this end of the string over here
sees another end of a string over here
it doesn't know it's part of the same
string all it knows is it found another
string another
end another end to annihilate with so
once you you introduce string
interactions you are committed to
something new you're committed to Clos
strings every theory of strings always
has closed strings you can write
theories of closed strings that don't
have open strings but you can't write
theories of open strings that don't have
closed strings so there's something more
General well I don't know if the right
word is General is something
um if you had to make a prediction about
String Theory it would not be that there
are open strings but it would be that
there are closed strings there's no way
around the closed strings in string
theory there are ways around the open
strings so the next thing we're going to
have to do after we work out this and
figure out what open strings are like
we're going to work out closed strings I
will tell you the answer right now open
strings often behave like photons closed
strings behave like gravitons there is
no theory of strings which doesn't have
gravitons there are theories of strings
which don't have uh
photons but uh we'll come to that next
time for more please visit us at
stanford.edu